Guide to the William Beckford Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Other Papers, 1755-1967; Series IV; 2.21; (6 boxes)
  - Fonthill Abbey: related material
    - Prints and Photographs
      - Sketches (reproductions), 1957, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 185)
      - Photographs, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 186-87)
    - "Refreshments at Fonthill Abbey." Printed bill of fare, 1823 (Box 9, Folder 188)
    - Tribute dinners at Fonthill. Invitations and menu, 1823-24 (Box 9, Folder 189)
  - Genealogy
    - Brief outline of Beckford genealogy, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 190)
    - "Succinct Memoirs of the Family of Beckford with Genealogical Tables", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 191)
    - "Table Showing the Immediate Paternal Connexion [sic] of William Beckford, Esquire", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 192-93)
      EMPTY FOLDERS: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 13, folder 281
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 194)
  - Lansdown Tower
    - Lansdown Tower Restoration, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 195)
    - "The Battle of Lansdown." The Athenaeum, 1844 (Box 9, Folder 196)
    - Sketches, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 197-98)
    - Photographs, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 199)
    - Slides (with slides of Fonthill Abbey), 1967 (Box 9, Folder 200)
    - "Lansdown Tower." The Illustrated London News
      See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 275
  - Miscellaneous writings
    - "Bath." The Imperial Gazetter of England and Wales, 1866 (Box 9, Folder 201)
    - Carter, John. " Two Beckford Collections." The Colophon (offprint), 1939 Mar (Box 9, Folder 202)
    - [Gibbon]. Comments on Edward Gibbon by William Beckford and Virginia Woolf (unknown compiler): typescript (Box 9, Folder 203)
    - Higginson, Henry. "A Visit to Steepleton House--The Home of Peter Beckford." The Sportsman, 1934 Jan (Box 9, Folder 204)
    - "John Francis, Publisher of The Athenaeum ." The Athenaeum, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 205)
    - The Land We Live In (Part XVIII): Bath, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 206)
    - Stirling, W. "The Cloister Life of Charles V." The Quarterly Review, 1852 Dec (Box 9, Folder 207)
    - Tomb of William Beckford: holograph description, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 208)
    - Tomb of William Beckford (d. 1731), Thomas Beckford, etc.: inscription (holograph copy), 1844 (Box 9, Folder 209)
    - Watts, Susanna. Tasso's Jerusalem: Proposal, For Publishing by subscription a New Translation of the Gerusalemme Liberata, Dedicated to William Beckford, Esq., of Fonthill, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 210)
    - Miscellaneous, 1930, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 211-13)
  - Prints and photographs
    See also: Box 9, folders 184-87, 197-200
    - Beckford, Margaret, Lady (?), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 214)
    - Beckford, William (1709-1770), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 215-17)
    - Beckford, William (1760-1844), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 218-19)
    - Beckford Estate, Jamaica (slides), 1951 (Box 9, Folder 220)
    - Beckford titles, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 221)
  - Sketch of William Beckford's tomb, Lansdown Cemetery (watercolor by unidentified artist), 1877 Aug 5 (Box 9, Folder 221a)
  - Vathek
    - Dehan, Richard. Vathek ("Liberally Adapted from the Romance of William Beckford"): notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 222)
    - Note on Vathek and Italy (Box 10, Folder 223)
    - "Vathek." The Athenaeum, 1909 Nov 29 (Box 10, Folder 224-25)
    - "'Vathek': The Henley Papers." The Athenaeum, 1909 Dec 25 (Box 10, Folder 226)
    - The Lausanne edition of Vathek
      - Carter, John. "The Lausanne Edition of Beckford's Vathek ": typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 227)
      - "Journal de Lausanne." (Transcription of first number: (December 2, 1986): holograph, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 228)
      - "Notes copied from manuscripts attached to the copy of Lausanne edition belonging to Monsieur Ch. Ph. Dumont": holograph, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 229)
      - "Notes on the Lausanne Edition of Vathek, in reference to the so called Chevannes Copy" (notes by Rowland Burdon-Muller): holograph notebook (Box 10, Folder 230)
      - Notes on "Journal de Lausanne" and Edouard-Luois Chevannes (by Rowland Burdon-Muller?) (Box 10, Folder 231)
  - William Beckford (1709-1770)
    - Biographical Tribute. Printed broadside, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 232)
    - United East-India Company enlistment vouchers, signed by William Beckford, 1763 (Box 10, Folder 233-34)
    - Summons to appear before William Beckford as alderman, 1768 Apr 23 (Box 10, Folder 235)
    - Disposition of Michael Kimerer (signed by Beckford), 1769 Dec 12 (Box 10, Folder 236)
    - "Instructions Given to Sir Robert Ladbroke, Knt., William Beckford, Esquire, Representations of the City of London: By Their Constituents." Printed broadside, 1769 Feb 10 (Box 10, Folder 237)
    - "To the Memory of William Beckford, Esq., Who Died June 21, 1770, Aged 65." Included in holograph manuscript entitled "Manuscript Poetry" (author unknown), n.d. (Box 10, Folder 238)
  - William Beckford (1760-1844) (articles)
    - Alexander, Boyd. Trumbull Lecture on William Beckford of Fonthill: typescript (Box 10, Folder 239)
    - Anton, P. "The Author of Vathek: The Story of a Magnificent Idler." The People's Friend, 1898 Jan 16-17 (Box 10, Folder 240)
    - "The Author of Vathek ." Time, 1883 Apr (Box 10, Folder 241)
    - "The Caliph of Fonthill." The Times Literary Supplement (photocopy), 1932 Nov 3 (Box 10, Folder 242)
    - "A Critical Study of the Works of William Beckford:" typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 243)
    - Jaloux, Edmund. "La jeunesse de William Beckford": holograph manuscript (Box 10, Folder 244)
    - Lansdown, Henry Venn. "Recollections of the Late William Beckford, Bath... .": holograph notebook (with letter from Charlotte Lansdown), 1838 (Box 10, Folder 245)
    - "The Late William Beckford." The Mirror, 1844 May 11 (Box 10, Folder 246)
    - "The Late William Beckford, Esq." (obituary). The Athenaeum, 1844 May 18 (Box 10, Folder 247)
    - "A Literary Millionaire" (review of Memoirs of William Beckford of Fonthill ), 1859 Feb 5 (Box 10, Folder 248)
    - "Mr. Beckford and Fonthill." Chambers' Edinburgh Journal, 1844 Aug (Box 10, Folder 249)
    - "Mr. Beckford and Fonthill Abbey." The Mirror, 1835 Sep 12 (Box 10, Folder 250)
    - Moussa-Mahmoud, Fatma. "A Monument to the Author of Vathek." Études Anglaises (offprint), n.d. (Box 10, Folder 251)
    - Moussa-Mahmoud, Fatma. Review of André Parreux, William Beckford, Auteur de Vathek (1760-1844) Cairo Studies in English, 1961-62 (Box 10, Folder 252)
    - "New Books." Review of Beckford's Recollections of an Excursion to the Monasteries of Alcaba and Batalba, 1835 Jul 18 (Box 10, Folder 253)
    - North, William. "Memoir" of William Beckford for Vathek (London, 1849 edition) (Box 10, Folder 254)
    - Oliphant, Mrs. "William Beckford and His Sons" (excerpt on the Beckford Library), 1857 (Box 10, Folder 255)
    - Parreaux, André. Portugal in the Works of William Beckford
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 256-57)
      - Typescript, bound (Box 11, Folder 258)
    - Sizer, Theodore. "William Beckford and His American Property." Yale University Library Gazette (offprint), 1964 Jul (Box 11, Folder 259)
    - Watson, Francis J. B. "Beckford, Mme. De Pompadour, The Duc de Bouillon, and the Taste for Japanese Lacquer in Eighteenth-Century France", 1963 (Box 11, Folder 260)
    - Whibley, Charles. "The Caliph of Fonthill." The New Review, 1897 Jan (Box 11, Folder 261)
    - "William Beckford, Esq., of Fonthill." The European Magazine and London Review, 1797 (Box 11, Folder 262)
    - "W. Beckford, Esq." (obituary). The Athenaeum, 1844 May 11 (Box 11, Folder 263)
    - "William Beckford and Vathek" (outline of a short article) (Box 11, Folder 264)
  - Newspaper clippings
    Box 14 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - William Beckford, 1910-62 (Box 11, Folder 265)
    - Book reviews, 1928-62 (Box 11, Folder 266)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-67 (Box 11, Folder 267)
  - Beckford film (16 mm), 1966; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002109979063)
    The film is accompanied by a soundtrack (two versions one reel-to-reel audio tape, each version on a different track). The film features scenes associated with William Beckford in Bath, England. The film was planned and produced by Andrew Barnett and Alan Scott, students at the Kingswood School in Bath, during the 1966 Bath Festival which was devoted to Beckford.
    Accompanied by a typescript description of the film, its scenes, projection and sound synchronization instructions, and distinctions between the two soundtracks; an undated autopgrah manuscript letter, signed, from Barnett to James T. Babb describing the film; and an autograph manuscript note, unsigned, describing the film.
    Box 14: Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Beckford film soundtrack, 1966; 1; 01:15:09; The program is distorted at times. The program is in silence from about 11:07-20:00. (Box 14, Item barcode 39002109979071)
    This is a soundtrack (two versions one reel-to-reel audio tape, each version on a different track) that accompanies the 16 mm film. The film features scenes associated with William Beckford in Bath, England. The film was planned and produced by Andrew Barnett and Alan Scott, students at the Kingswood School in Bath, during the 1966 Bath Festival which was devoted to Beckford.
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- Oversize, 1795-1960; 3.5; (2 boxes)
  - Personal Papers
    - Indentures
      - Bond of Francis Beckford to Thomas Beckford, 1749 Aug 24 (Box 12, Folder 268)
  - Other Papers
    - Account book for South Sea stock, etc. (unidentified, with information about Beckford's lease of Schodelhan Farm), [1795] (Box 12, Folder 269)
    - Beckford's Library - disposition lists
      - Barnbougle Castle [photocopies], [1960, n.d.] (Box 12, Folder 270-71)
    - Fonthill Abbey: Articles and News Clippings
      - "Fonthill Abbey and Domain," Evans and Ruffy Farmer's Journal, 1822 Oct 21 (Box 12, Folder 272)
      - Lewis, Kensington, "Fonthill Abbey - The Topaz Vase," Advertisement to the Edition of The Morning Chronicle [holograph], n.d. (Box 12, Folder 273)
      - "Sale of the Beckford Collection," The Illustrated London News, 1845 Nov 29 (Box 12, Folder 274)
      - "Lansdown Tower," The Illustrated London News, 1845 Nov 22 (Box 12, Folder 275)
  - Personal Papers
    - Indentures
      - Bond of Julius Beckford to Francis Beckford, 1754 Dec 19 (Box 13, Folder 276)
  - Other Papers
    - Fonthill Abbey: Articles and News Clippings
      - "Fonthill Mansion, Wilts, To be Sold...," The Courier, 1807 Aug 11 (Box 13, Folder 277)
      - "Magnificent and Valuable Effects, Fonthill to be Sold by Auction...," The Sun, 1801 Jul 27 (Box 13, Folder 278)
      - "Strange Freaks of a Millionaire," Exeter News Letter, 1859 Feb 28 (Box 13, Folder 279)
    - Fonthill Abbey: Related Material
      - "A view at Fonthill Abbey" (with dwarf), (lithograph), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 280)
      - Fonthill Abbey. Colored engraving (print) by R. Havell and Son; drawn by H. Gartineau from sketch by T. Higham (Box 13, Folder 280)
    - Genealogy
      - "Table Showing the Immediate Paternal Connexion [sic] of William Beckford, Esquire" (with explanatory notes [holograph]), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 281)